A Guide to the Papers of the Nolting Family of Brackett's Farm, Louisa County, Va.
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of the Nolting Family of Brackett's Farm, Louisa County, Va.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
13944
7 cubic boxes, oversize materials
George C. Nolting
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquistion Information
The papers were a gift of George C. Nolting for the Elizabeth Aiken Nolting Charitable Foundation, Gordonsville, Va., 2007 Aug. 17.
Biographical/Historical Information
The papers are primarily related to Carl H. Nolting and Elizabeth Aiken Nolting and other members of the Nolting family such as Carl's brothers, Frederick E. Nolting, Otto Nolting and sisters, Loulie Nolting, Mrs. R. Tate Irvine, Dr. Margaret Nolting and Carl Nolting's nephew G. Freeland Peter.
Major George Frederick William Nolting was Carl H. Nolting's grandfather and he came to Virginia in 1839. His son was Emil Otto Nolting who exported tobacco and built the "Monticola" estate in Howardsville, Virginia in 1887. The Film, "Virginia" was filmed there starring Fred MacMurray and Madeleine Carroll. He married Susanne Horne.
Carl H. Nolting owned the Midloch Pony Farm in Trevillians, Virginia. He was also former chairman of the State Commission of Game and Inland Fisheries and Chairman of the Louisa Board of Supervisors. He was also involved with the Democratic Party, the telephone company, Chesapeake and Ohio Railways, oil drillings in Texas, banks, and mines across the United States. He was also interested in many farms including Harkwood.
Elizabeth Aiken Nolting lived on Bracketts Farm in Trevillians, Virginia and created the Green Springs Inc. She was also active in the American Red Cross. [1945]
Scope and Content
This collection is not fully processed and at this time contains 7 cubic boxes and a handful of oversize materials. There is significant correspondence and financial information for Carl H. Nolting, his niece, Elizabeth Aiken Nolting and other members of the Nolting family. Most of the correspondence is related to Carl Nolting and his business of acquiring and selling Welsh and Shetland ponies but also includes his interests in the telephones, banks, oil, railroads, mining, real estate, stocks and politics.
Elizabeth Aiken Nolting of Brackett's Farm in Trevillians, Virginia, was active in the American Red Cross during World War II and established the historic district for Green Springs, Virginia where Brackett's Farm is located. There is information about farming, archeological history, Brackett's Farm, Green Springs, Inc. and information about Virginia estates and historical sites including Kennilworth, Castle Hill, Cobham Park. Grace Episcopal Church, St. John's Chapel and the founding of the Keswick Hunt Club.
The correspondence mentions the hard times for miners and the shutting down of the Sulphur Mining & Railway Company and the San Rafael Mines in 1912.
There is also correspondence about the loss of Carl Nolting's political seat in Louisa, Virginia in 1911.
There is interesting correspondence between Carl Nolting and Duncan Wright pertaining to evidence against the Scotsman for having relations with a Miss Nichols and subsequent information about establishing an anti-nuptial contract with his wife. (Frederick Wilmer Sims letter) The correspondence also includes a letter from Carl Nolting that accuses a detective of paying the "darkies" to tell a different version of the story against Wright.
Important correspondents include Claude Swanson, Richard Evelyn Byrd, Governor E. Lee Trinkle, and Thomas S. Martin.
Other correspondents are customers of the Pony Farm and friends and colleagues from his various interests, such as Henry Lee Dean, J. B. Baylor, [Matty] Bolling, John A. Curtis, Edwin P. Cox, W. C. Bryan, Porter Emerson Browne, Julian Morris, [ ] Hilleary, W. D. Gillespie and Parker Jones.
There is personal correspondence from Carl Nolting's mother and other family members including information about a lawsuit between Carl Nolting and Loulie Nolting.
There is a biographical sketch of the Eugene Davis and Morris family.
There is also a typed manuscript by Amélie Rives, titled "The Ballad of Hell."
There is information about naturopathic medicine from one of the Nolting family members (Mark Harrison Nolting) who obtains a degree in this field.
There are photographs and information about Civil War Re-enactments.
There are news clippings, photographs, photo albums, postcards, address books, copy books, school notebooks and logbooks for Bracketts' farm and other record books.
There is a news clipping about the Noltings generations passing on the role of Belgian Consul starting with Emil Otto Nolting, to his son Otto Nolting, to his brother, Frederick E. Nolting (given the honor of being the Knight of the Order of Leopold) and to Frederick's son, A. S. Buford Nolting in 1950.
There are also news clippings about the artwork of Chica Tenney and Lindsay Nolting.
Also included in this collection are horseshow ribbons, a horse bit, and printing blocks for various catalogs. There is also printed material including a history of the Watson Family.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by topics and types of materials and is chronological within each folder.
Contents List
- Brackett's Farm (Box 1)
- Brackett's Farm notebook (Box 1)
- Brackett's Farm (Box 1)
- Brackett's Dam (Box 1)
- Brackett's Well (Box 1)
- Business cards (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Carl Nolting (Box 1)
  (Correspondence folders include telephone contracts)
- Correspondence, Carl Nolting (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Carl Nolting (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Carl Nolting (Box 1)
- Personal Correspondence, Carl Nolting (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Carl Nolting and Henry Lee Dean, 1913-1915 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Carl Nolting and Duncan Wright, 1911 Sept. 1; 1913 May 22, 1915 March 9 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Carl Nolting and Richard Evelyn Byrd, 1911 June 15, 1923; n.d. (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Carl Nolting and Governor E. Lee Trinkle, 1924 Jan 31; n.y. June 4 (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Carl Nolting, catalog requests (Box 1)
- Personal Correspondence, Elizabeth Aiken Nolting (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Elizabeth Aiken Nolting (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Elizabeth Aiken Nolting (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Elizabeth Aiken Nolting (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Elizabeth Aiken Nolting (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Elizabeth Aiken Nolting (Box 1)
- Elizabeth Aiken Nolting school essays (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Scotchtown (Box 1)
- Correspondence, Mark Harrison Nolting and Naturopathic Medicine (Box 1)
- Eugene Davis Biographical Sketch (and Morris family), 1824-1893 (Box 1)
- Eugene Davis Biographical Sketch (and Morris family), 1824-1893 (Box 1)
- Financial Correspondence (Box 2)
- Blank Financial Forms (Box 2)
- Financial, G. Freeland Peter Estate (Box 2)
- Financial checkbooks (Box 2)
- Financial (Box 2)
- Financial (Box 2)
- Financial (Box 2)
- Financial (Box 2)
- Financial (Box 2)
- Financial (Box 2)
- Financial (Box 2)
- Financial (Box 2)
- Financial (Box 2)
- Financial (Box 2)
- Financial (Box 2)
- Financial (Box 2)
- Financial (Box 2)
- Financial (Box 3)
- Financial (Box 3)
- Financial (Box 3)
- Financial (Box 3)
- Financial (Box 3)
- Financial (Box 3)
- Financial (Box 3)
- Financial stock (Box 3)
- Legal deeds (Box 3)
- Carl Nolting deed to Bolling Hall, 1914 July 16 (Box 3)
- Deed to Chesapeake & Ohio Railway, 1920 May 1 (Box 3)
- Deed on the sale of "Monticola" receipt, 1911 Jan. 18 (Box 3)
- Loulie W. Nolting v. Carl H. Nolting, 1913 July 2 (Box 3)
- Green Springs Wills Memorial Church (Box 3)
- Green Springs book, 1975 (Box 3)
  (List of names of people taking tours)
- Green Springs (Box 3)
- Green Springs Manuscript (Box 3)
  (History and photograph)
- Green Springs Manuscript (Box 3)
- Green Springs (Box 3)
- Historical Green Springs Preservation Board (Box 3)
- Green Springs, John Bazlin (Box 3)
  (Natural history, Indians, archaeology)
- Green Springs, John Bazlin (Box 3)
  (Includes a paper, "The Case of the Laborer from Louisa" by Peter Wallenstein, 1990)
- Farming (Box 3)
- Grace Episcopal Church (Box 3)
- Railway (Box 3)
- St. John's Chapel (Box 3)
- St. John's Chapel (Box 3)
- Tudor Place Foundation (Box 3)
- Thomas S. Watson (Box 3)
  (Including calculations from Dickenson map)
- Manuscript "Ballad of Hell" by Amélie Rives (Box 4)
- Manuscript book - Dutch (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous items of Nolting family (Box 4)
- Miscellaneous poem (Box 4)
- News clippings (Box 4)
- News clippings (Box 4)
  (Obituaries)
- News clippings, Elizabeth Aiken Nolting, Keswick Hunt Club, Castle Hill, G. Freeland Peter, China (Box 4)
- News clippings, Harkwood, 1986 (Box 4)
- Address book (Box 4)
- Autograph book (Box 4)
- Copy book of Otto Nolting (Box 4)
- Notebook of Nolting family member (Box 4)
- Notebooks of Lulie Nolting (Box 4)
- Notebook, Linden Lane Farm (Box 4)
- Notebooks, school (Box 4)
- Notebook of songs (Box 4)
- Stampbook (Box 4)
- Journal of letters of Carl Nolting (Box 4)
- Civil War re-enactment photographs (Box 4)
- Negatives (Box 4)
- Photographs, Coaching (Box 4)
- Photographs, Black and white on black acidic paper, 2 sheets (Box 4)
- Photographs of "Brackett's Farm", Color (Box 4)
- Photographs, Black and white (Box 4)
- Photographs, Black and white (Box 4)
- Photographs, Black and white (damaged, curling) (Box 4)
- Photographs of the Nolting Families, Color (Box 4)
- Photographs, In magnetic pages (Box 4)
- Photographs, In magnetic pages (Box 4)
- Oversize Photographs (Box 4)
- Scrapbooks and Photograph Albums, (3) (Box 5)
- Postcards (Box 5)
  (Places in Virginia)
- Postcards (Box 5)
- Books, General (Box 6)
  Tile Drainage by W. I. Chamberlain 1891
  How To Argue and Win by Grenville Kleise, Funk & Wagnells Co. 1912
  Welsh Stud Book v. IV 1905
  American Shetland Stud Book v. 12 1913
  American Shetland Stud Book v. XIII 1914
  The International Lily Register
- Almanacs, Atlases, Encyclopedias (Box 6)
  Dr. Miles' Weather Almanac 1925
  Bacon's Up to Date Atlas and Guide to London
  Emminent Virginian Hardesty's Encyclopedia[Manuscript] Oversize
- Local Information, Flyers and Brochures, Maps (Box 6)
  A History of Louisa County, Va. by Malcolm H. Harris M. D. announcement of a new edition
  Monograph of a Country Home 1974
  Memorandum of Five Estates
  Map of Louisa County, Virginia
  The Commonwealth, The Magazine of Virginia April 1961
  The Garden Club of Virginia presents the Thirty-Fifth Annual Lily Show 1977
  Virginia Harvest Celebration Sept. 19, 1999
  Piedmont Service Station advertisement, Gordonsville, Va. 1930
  Visit the Great Historic Plantations James River
  The Madisons of Montpelier Robert A. Rutland 1986
  Fall Dinner at Monticello Nov. 1, 1985
  1959 Annual Report Louisa County
  University of Virginia Alumni News v. VI number 15 Mar 27, 1918; v. VI number 20 June 5, 1918
  Magnolia Farm H. G. Higgins
- Horses (Box 6)
  Midloch Pony Farm Catalogs no. 3 and no.5
  Pine Crest Pony Farms Catalog
  The American Shetland Pony Club Rules, Constitution, Scale of Points and List of Members 1914
  Shetland Pony Sale
  Price List The Implement Company
- Telephone Directories (Box 6)
  Fredericksburg Louisa Telephone Directory 1932
- Railroads (Box 6)
  Sixty-Seventh Annual Report of the Louisville & Nashville Railroad Company Dec. 31 1917
  Twenty-Second Annual Report Norfolk and Western Railway Co. Dec. 31, 1917
  Ninety-Second Annual Report of the Atlantic Coast Line Railroad Company
- Government Publications (Box 6)
  Department of Agriculture and Immigration of Virginia no. 127 April 1918 and no. 296; July 1918 no.130; Jan. 1930 Aug 1932
  Report of the Commission to Study the Condition of the Farmers of Virginia Jan. 1930
  U. S. Department of Agriculture's Natural Resources Programs May 1998
  The Story of the Cattle Fever Tick Washington Government Printing Office 1917
  Regulations Concerning Cleaning and Special Preparation of Bituminous Coal
  Washington Government Printing Office Publication no. 20 1918
  America's Coal Problem in 1918 Washington Government Printing Office 1918
  Use Potatoes to Save Wheat U. S. Department of Agriculture 1918
  Virginia Agricultural Experiment Station Bulletin 251 Nov. 1925
- Green Springs (Box 6)
  Historic Green Springs Inc. South Anna Monitoring Project Feb. 2003; Dec. 2003; Dec. 2004
- Cultural Arts (Box 6)
  "That's That" Thirty-Sixth Annual Production of The Mask and Wig Club of the University of Pennsylvania 1889–1924
  National Cathedral School programs
  National Theatre programs
  Happy Music Hours Robert Lawrence
  School Song Dear NCS music sheet
- Other (Box 6)
  The Gully Plug Spring/Summer 1998
  The Revolution in Middle Virginia v. I-VI (Oversize)
  The Cause of the War by Rev. J. L. Early
  The Journals of Mary Jane Boggs Holladay 1851–1884
  The Angus Handbook
  Three States Realty Company July 15, 1918
  Alabama Consolidated Coal and Iron Co.
  Alfred Emmanuel Smith
  D. W. Griffith presents America 1924
  Watson family history
  Maps of Kentucky, Tennessee; and other states in the U. S.
  Newspapers: The Furrow 1930
- Printing blocks for catalogs (Box 7)
- Horse bit (Box 7)
- Horseshow ribbons (Box 7)
- Oversize items
  Architectural drawings, certificates, photographs and album pages